Are you tophi? No, not toffee. Although
that does actually sound pretty good. A
to fi tophi. Well, if you don't know,
don't worry about it because you'll find
out soon enough. And it very much
explains that title why being normal
weight could actually be speeding you up
towards illness and a premature death.
But I'd like to take it a step further
because there's even instances where a
person could be overweight and be
healthier than a normal weight
individual. Even assuming smoking,
exercise, and all that jazz is the same.
Don't believe me? Well, I haven't lost
my mind. I'll show you. You may or may
not be aware that there's an incredibly
popular metric used in clinics and in
research called BMI or body mass index.
That metric is extremely simple to
calculate. It's merely your weight in
kilograms divided by your height in
meters squared. A lot of people,
especially in the USA, are at least
overweight, but a good amount are also
obese. Meaning, as BMI creeps closer to
30, we're talking severely overweight.
Here's the thing, though. I'm
overweight. And if you're thinking,
"What?
You're overweight? How?"
Then first of all, thank you. And if
you're thinking, "Yep, seems about
right." Then meet me in the playground
at 2 PM after Mrs. Schusters's class. I
have some choice words for you, and I've
been practicing my karate punk. Kidding
aside, I have a BMI of about 27, which
puts me in the overweight category
according to this BMI metric. since it
only considers weight as a whole, it's
flawed because it doesn't distinguish
between muscle weight and fat weight. In
fact, when looking at the predictive
ability of BMI to predict cardioabolic
mortality, that's a fancy way of saying
that your body is strained in the risk
of dying prematurely. And you compare
against a metric that takes fat into
account called relative fat mass. The
relative fat mass measurement is more
sensitive and predictive. We can see
that mortality risk on the vertical axis
here. So women up top, men on the
bottom, and the horizontal axis is the
relative fat mass measurement with risk
slowly ebbing upwards until it really
takes off somewhere above 40% RFM for
women and above 30% RFM for men. So what
I'm getting at here is that you can have
a normal BMI, a normal weight, or less
than a BMI of 25, but still be over fat.
You may have actually heard of that
concept before, but what I'd like to
introduce you to is to take it a step
further based on this study. So, let me
revisit this first thing that I asked
you. Are you tophi? No,
not toffee. That stands for thin
outside, fatter inside, or as some
people call it, skinny fat. Some ways to
tell is to calculate your BMI using a
formula that I discussed earlier. And
here it is again. In addition, measure
your waist circumference using a tape
measure. If your BMI is less than 25 and
your waist circumference is larger than
88 cm for women or 102 cm for men, then
you might qualify as being higher risk
as a tophi. Don't worry though, there's
some simple solutions. And even so, you
may still not be at risk because of this
second study that we're about to go
over. By the way, if you want a more
in-depth checklist to determine if you
fall under a higher risk based on some
of the simple athome measurements and
answering a few simple questions, I
offer a more in-depth checklist for
free. Uh, I'll be releasing it to my
email list in 2 days from this video
release. So, be sure to join there. or
if it's past the 2-day mark and you're
watching this, join my free community.
Both links are in the description. It's
also in the free community. Okay. So,
how can a person who is overweight,
let's actually take it a step further,
they even have more body fat than you,
yet they might be healthier. How is that
possible? Well, in this second study,
the researchers quantified the body fat
into three compartments. visceral fat,
so fat around the organs. Abdominal
subcutaneous fat, so fat around your
midsection, just under the skin, and
glutammoral fat, fat around your thighs
and butt. Then they adjusted for BMI,
meaning that they wanted to find the
relationship between these fat depots,
these three fat depots, independent of
weight. We can see that here we have two
major diseases up top, the subgroups
split by sex and the BMI adjusted fat
depot. and then a forest plot indicating
risk of each disease. If the squares
move to the right, that's increased
risk. And if they move to the left,
that's reduced risk. So, if we take a
closer look, it seems clear regardless
of sex, visceral fat is linked to
diabetes and heart disease.
Fascinatingly though, abdominal
subcutaneous fat or ASAT there is either
neutral or a relatively slightly
increased risk of diabetes except in
women. And finally, the most surprising
of all, there's a fat storage depot that
reduces risk, the glutofmoral fat or G
fat there. So, this tells us a few
things. One, visceral fat is harmful to
health. Probably not a huge shock for
those in the know. Two, not all fat is
created equal. So, some fat is not
detrimental to health, at least not to
these metrics. Although it might not be
great to have excess as it will probably
stress the joints as a counter. And
three, conceptually this identifies that
a person who is normal weight and even
normal healthy relative fat mass, the
more exact measure could be in worse
health situation than a person
significantly more overfat than them
simply because of the distribution of
their fat. Now, we're a few degrees
removed from BMI, right? I mean, we've
we're not just assessing weight. Uh
we're not just assessing body fat
through relative fat mass. We're
assessing the position of the fat even
independent of weight. So, that raises
this question of why why do these fat
depots diverge so strongly? And how
should we think about all of this? And
if you have more visceral fat, what
could you do to reverse that? Well, for
some of that, let's lean on this
scientific review. In this review, the
researchers describe the differences in
these fat depots and what might explain
the differences in harm. So, I'll admit
it, there are still some mysteries, but
we do know a few things. For example,
when taking tissues from all three of
these fat depots, they each have
different gene signatures, meaning
visceral fat expresses a different set
of genes compared to glutammoral fat. In
fact, that phenomenon may be all the way
from development because these fat
depots may originate from different stem
cells as an embryo. In fact, in fact,
when growing these fat cells in the
exact same metabolic environment, some
of the gene signatures are still unique
to that fat depot. That offers some
clues, but we also have some more
physiologically concrete differences.
One of those is fat turnover. They
mentioned that abdominal subcutaneous
and likely visceral fat have faster
turnover than glutmoral fat depots.
Meaning that when bound by hormones like
the stress hormone cortisol, the cell
dumps fat molecules into ectopic sites.
So meaning areas fat shouldn't normally
be like muscle and the liver and other
organ systems, thereby promoting insulin
resistance and cardiovascular risk. In
addition, these cells are more prone to
undergo hypertrophy or enlarging. On the
other hand, the glutammoral fat acts as
a protective buffer which is much slower
in its release of fat molecules and
having a robust capacity to take up fats
from the bloodstream without releasing
them back. They also retain their
hyperplasia ability meaning that the
generation of new fat cells creating
more fat cells to retain fat instead of
dumping into the bloodstream and to the
you know muscle and liver. So within a
tissue we're getting wildly different
reactions. Isn't that fascinating?
Okay. So how do we think about all this
and what do we do before that? If you're
wanting more ways to assess risk beyond
the free template that I mentioned
earlier, I have an extended analysis of
this video that you're watching along
with an accompanying article. And in it,
I'm going to describe another way to
assess risk from home along with the
progression of risk. I'm also going to
go over some more of how these fats
differ, the mechanisms, and a particular
treatment that potently redistributes
fat and leads to significant health
improvements by simply moving it. If
you're interested, check out the
Physionic Insiders in the description
box. You'll get access to all that, plus
so much more. You can see the list right
here, all included again in the
description box if you're interested.
Here's how I'd think about all this.
One, on average, being overweight, or
more specifically over fat, is still a
greater risk than being normal weight.
However, that assumes that the fat
distribution is about the same. If a
person has less overall fat or equal
amounts of fat, but they have a
disproportionately greater level of
visceral fat, they are likely at greater
health risk, at least cardiomatabolic
risk. the use of tophi, no not toffee
template in the email list and in the
free community to give you a better
overall idea of your risk if you're
unsure. And number two, fat is not all
the same. The location of the fat
independent of your weight makes a
tremendous difference on your risk.
Number three, the review that we went
over mentions that simple nutrition
adjustments like just about any diet,
but calorically restricted leads to
preferentially reductions in this
especially harmful visceral fat. And if
you're in the normal weight category
with higher visceral fat, I would
strongly recommend filling in some of
that weight loss with muscle by
implementing a resistance training
program. So you're attacking the issue
from two directions. So, less visceral
fat and more metabolically demanding
muscle tissue. In fact, I've covered an
especially effective group of foods and
a diet that has had an outsized impact
on melting visceral fat off of your
body. Check it out right here. And for
those of you that are going to say, I'd
pronounce it toi and not tophi. That
wouldn't work for the joke. Come on,
bro. Play along. I'll catch you later.